Okay בוקר
טוב *boker tov* today's דף *daf* is מ"ד *mem dalet*, מנחות Menachot.
*Menachos* 44, we pick up towards the bottom of very bottom of
מ"ג עמוד ב' *mem gimmel amud bet*. It is תניא היה רבי
מאיר אומר Tanya, haya Rabbi Meir omer, *tanya hayah Rabbi Meir omer*
two lines before the widest lines. And we're right in the middle
of a major section of great אגדתא *aggadata* about ציצית tzitzis. *tzitzit*
and some of the understanding about the religious purpose and meaning of
it and also very relevant הלכות *halachos* about ציצית tzitzis. *tzitzit* as
well. Okay, so תניא Tanya, היה רבי מאיר אומר haya Rabbi Meir
omer. גדול עונשו של לבן יותר מעונשו של תכלת techelet, *tanya hayah
Rabbi Meir omer gadol onsho shel lavan yoter meonsho shel tcheiles*. The
punishment for not wearing the white strings of the ציצית tzitzis *tzitzit*
is greater than the punishment for somebody who does not wear the
blue strings of the ציצית tzitzis *tzitzit*.
Why? Because it's a lot easier to wear the white ones. So
your negligence is just and your fault and your blameworthiness is just
that much greater because it was so much easier for you to
do. משל למה הדבר דומה *mashal l'mah hadavar domeh*? To what can
this be compared? למלך בשר ודם שאמר לשני עבדיו *l'melech basar v'dam
sheomer lishnei avadav*. Like a human king who says to his two
servants, לאחד אמר הבא לי חותם של טיט *l'echad amar havei li
chosam shel tit*. To one he says, bring me a seal made
out of plaster, and these would be a seals which would be
worn by either animals or slaves to show to whom the animal
belonged and to whom the slave would belong. So I want you
to bring me, and presumably also bring for me to use on
my slave or for you to be using for your own identification,
one out of a plaster. ולאחד אמר הבא לי חותם של זהב
*u'le'echad amar havei li chosam shel zahav*. Bring me one out of
gold. ופשעו שניהם ולא הביאו *u'pashu shneihem v'lo heiviu*. And both of
them were negligent and they did not do what the king asked.
איזה מהן עונשו מרובה *eizeh mehen onsho merubah*? Who is deserving of
a greater punishment? הוי אומר זה שאמר לו הבא לי חותם של
טיט ולא הביא *havei omer zeh sheamar lo havei li chosam shel
tit v'lo heivi*. It would clearly be the one that would said
bring me the one of plaster that was so much easier and
you did not do it. תכלת techelet, *tcheiles* is of course gold
is so much harder, תכלת *tcheiles* is so much harder. So I'm
not sure we actually needed the משל *mashal* to understand that there's
greater negligence in the case of the white that the white is
easier than the תכלת *tcheiles*, but what the משל *mashal* does provide
us with is again something about the symbolism and the power of
ציצית tzitzis *tzitzit*. It is something that you wear like these seals,
like these signs, and that
show to whom you belong, it shows something about your identity. The
slave belongs to the king, we belong to God. It is a
marker of identity. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues, two lines down now in the
widest lines. תניא Tanya היה רבי מאיר אומר haya Rabbi Meir omer,
*tanya haya Rabbi Meir omer* רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* used
to say, because we said just before תניא היה רבי מאיר אומר
haya Rabbi Meir omer. *tanya haya Rabbi Meir omer* here's another one
not exactly directly about ציצית tzitzit, *tzitzit*, not about ציצית tzitzit *tzitzit*
at all actually. חייב chayav אדם לברך מאה ברכות Brachos בכל יום
*chayav adam l'varech me'ah berachos bechol yom*. A person should make a
hundred ברכות Brachos *berachos* every day. שנאמר shene'emar, *shene'emar* as the פסוק
pasuk, *pasuk* says ועתה ישראל Yisrael. מה ה' אלהיך שואל מעמך *ve'ata
Yisrael mah Hashem Elokecha sho'el me'imach*. And now Israel, what does God
ask of you? So where do you see a hundred ברכות Brachos?
*berachos*? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, and this is certainly the most
common explanation, that you should not read the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* מה
ה' אלהיך שואל מעמך *mah Hashem Elokecha sho'el me'imach*—what does God ask
from you?—but מאה ה' אלהיך שואל מעמך *me'ah Hashem Elokecha sho'el me'imach*.
He asks from you a hundred ברכות Brachos *berachos*. What justifies such
a rereading of the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*? So there's a beautiful מהרש"א
*Maharsha*. The מהרש"א *Maharsha* says because this פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is one
that
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* has real difficulty with this פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*.
What is God asking from you? כי אם ליראה את ה' אלהיך
*ki im l'yirah et Hashem Elokecha*—only to fear God, to do all
of the מצוות mitzvos. *mitzvos* etc. etc., and lists this whole long
list of things which is a very, very, very big ask. So
what do you mean what does God ask from you as if
it's trivial what's being asked from us to fear God, to do
all of the מצוות Mitzvot, *mitzvos*? So that's what pushes רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* to read it in a different way. And
in a way, this is a beautiful second part of the מהרש"א
*Maharsha* which is so beautiful, that if God is asking from us
מאה *me'ah* a hundred ברכות Brachos *berachos*, through making those ברכות Brachos,
*berachos* and through having God in our consciousness throughout the entire
day at all these different moments when we have to ask for
things in the שמנה עשרה *Shemoneh Esrei*, when we eat for our
food, for מצוות Mitzvot *mitzvos*, all of those is the way we
achieve כי אם ליראה את ה' אלהיך *ki im l'yirah et Hashem
Elokecha*, the end of that פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. Very beautiful reading of
that.
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* also says that it could be we got to
a hundred because if you have the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* שואל *sho'el*
written with a ו' *vav*, there are actually 100 letters in the
פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. Okay, fine. That's very fascinating as well. Anyway, you
have to make a hundred ברכות Brachos *berachos*. How do you get
the hundred ברכות Brachos, *berachos*? Well let's see. Three שמנה עשרה *Shemoneh
Esreis*, 19 ברכות Brachos *berachos* in each שמנה עשרה *Shemoneh Esrei*, so
that's already gets you 57. And then you've got ברכת התורה *Birchas
HaTorah* and all the ברכות Brachos השחר *berachos hashachar* and ברכת קריאת
שמע Shema *birchas krias shema*. If you בענטשן *bench*, probably is not
so hard, you can do the math under a normal day to
get 100 ברכות Brachot, *berachos*. In. However, it's going to be a
lot harder on שבת, Shabbos which is what the גמרא Gemara says.
רבי חייא בריה דרב אוויא, Rabbi Chiya brei d'Rav Avya, רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya the son of רבי אוויא, Rabbi Avya, בשבתא וביומי טבי
b'Shabso u'vyomei Tovei on שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov when
the שמונה עשרהs Shmoneh Esrei would have seven ברכות each and not
19 ברכות each,
so how would they get enough ברכות? So it says טרח וממלי
לה באספרמקי ומגדי, tarach u'memali lei b'isparmaki u'megadi, they would go to
the effort, he would go to the effort, excuse me, and fill
up the 100 ברכות with like fragrances and delicacies, eating a lot
of different fruits, smelling various fragrances you make different ברכות about בשמים
besamim on, etc., etc. You know there would be people that would
always do a lot of smelling of snuff on שבת in order
to get in the 100 ברכות, also particularly יום כיפור Yom Kippur
where you also don't even
have ברכות that you make on food. Okay. תניא, we taught in
a ברייתא. Baraisa. So that was another היה רבי Rebbi, מאיר אומר.
A third one, very, very important הלכה halacha here. היה רבי Rebbi,
מאיר אומר, רבי Rebbi מאיר used to say, although some, this is
a תוספתא Tosefta and in the תוספתא Tosefta the גרסא girsa is
רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, although it's clearly being quoted here
because of the היה רבי מאיר אומר. תניא היה רבי מאיר אומר,
רבי מאיר used to say חייב אדם לברך שלוש ברכות בכל יום,
chayav adam l'varech shalosh brachos bechol yom, a person has to make
three ברכות, these are the ברכות of identity each day. אלו הן,
elu hen, and these are them: שעשני ישראל. she'asani Yisrael. Now the
actual גרסא girsa as we know, if you look at the footnote
here, is שלא עשני גוי, shelo asani goy, they did not make
me a גוי. goy. But you know for censors, for the purpose
of censors where there was times they did a lot of self-censorship
of the תלמוד, Talmud, so the non-Jews, you know the Christians, would
not be upset about it and burn it or or you know
or decide to censor it themselves. So we so rather than saying
I did not make me a non-Jew, which is saying a clear
negative statement about a non-Jew, say it more in the positive that
you have made me a ישראל. Which raises the question, but that's
I mean that's excuse me that's not obviously the הלכה, halacha, but
that is how it was censored, you know, to read to protect
ourselves from that criticism. Which does raise the question about why not
say it in the positive, and there definitely are some, particularly I
think in the Conservative movement, where they who frame it in the
positive. The problem with saying it in the positive is two parts.
Number one is, as we're going to see, there's like a, you
know, a gradation. שלא עשני גוי, shelo asani goy, שלא עשני עבד,
shelo asani eved, שלא עשני אשה. shelo asani isha. Obviously we'll get
there, but you know when you say שלא עשני גוי, shelo asani
goy, that doesn't it's still meaningful to say שלא עשני עבד, shelo
asani eved, and an עבד eved isn't a גוי goy but you're
still glad that you're not an עבד. eved. When you say שעשני
ישראל, she'asani Yisrael, it's no longer meaningful to say שעשני בן חורין.
she'asani ben chorin. So you'd have to like reverse the order. First
שעשני בן חורין she'asani ben chorin and then שעשני ישראל. she'asani Yisrael.
Nevertheless, you know, it's also I you know I think significant the
שלא shelo because often we the way we appreciate the gifts that
we have is appreciating what it would mean to be to not
have those gifts. So I think there's a reason why it was
with the שלא עשניs shelo asani here rather than the positive שעשני.
she'asani. It also should be noted that these ברכות parallel a famous
statement said by Thales who was a Greek philosopher. He said there
are three attributes for which I am grateful to Fortune, Fortune being
capitalized you know the god. I was born first human and not
animal, so notice that's both the positive and the negative.
Second man and not woman, so you get both again positive and
negative, and we'll see man not woman. And third Greek and not
barbarian. Okay, so interesting that that already existed in the, you know,
larger non-Jewish pagan culture similar type of a sentiment. Okay, so he
says first שלא עשני גוי. shelo asani goy. Number two שלא עשני
אשה, shelo asani isha, to not make me a woman. Which obviously,
you know, reflects I assume this is not coming as a surprise,
you know, to people, but the general, you know, rabbinic preferencing of
men over women not just in terms of, you know, societally that
they were advantaged, but also, you know, the sense that men have
a greater obligation in מצוות. Mitzvot And we can try to soften
that nowadays and, you know, deal with that and so on, but
there definitely was that פשט pshat assumption, you know, in the גמרא.
Gemara. There's a whole תשובה teshuvah of רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe
Feinstein where he makes it clear חס ושלום chas v'shalom to say
that there means there's different any different level of קדושה kedusha and
קדושת ישראל kedushas Yisrael and people have different functions and it doesn't
mean higher or lower, but you know clearly that idea was there
in חז"ל. Chazal.
So and of course
nowadays, you know, there's the whole that as people are aware, certainly
when I was younger going back 20, 30 years, an enormous amount
of literature about people that do not feel comfortable with saying the
שלא עשני אשה shelo asani isha ברכה bracha and whether alternative were
available and as we're going to see in a minute in the
גמרא Gemara here, there was some fluidity and flexibility in terms of
how to formulate certain ברכות, so there's an enormous amount of literature
there. In some שולס shuls they have switched to the positive, although
I mentioned some of the challenges with that. Some places they just
don't say them out loud in the שול shul because they're hurtful,
they can be hurtful or painful,
different types of possible approaches to that. One approach that I just
had was to read it more as a critique of society or
something to work on improving, meaning the recognition that even
today it is generally easier for men in society than it is
for women, but rather than reading it as a sort of so
you could be grateful that you have those advantages,
but rather than reading it that way which reemphasizes this type of
a
hierarchy and to read it as a type of a critique, to
read it as sensitizing us to the unfairness in society and maybe
calling upon us to address it. You could understand the same thing
regarding the שלא עשני עבד, Shelo Asani Eved, that there's still slavery
in society, and when we appreciate how horrific it is
for that phenomenon, then we should try to do everything we can
to eradicate it. So in the case of women, to eradicate the
injustices
and the that still exist within society. Anyway, lot a lot of
literature on this. Let's take a look back at the גמרא. Gemara
שלא עשני בור, Shelo Asani Bor, the third one is that you
did not make me an ignoramus. So notice by the way that
those two, the man and not woman,
the not woman not ignoramus, parallel from that statement I gave before
from Thales about man and not woman and Greek and not barbarian.
Okay,
רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov שמעיה לבריה, shamei livrei,
רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov heard his son דהוה
קמברך שלא עשני בור, d'hava k'mevarech Shelo Asani Bor, he made that
ברכה Bracha as it was originally appeared in this ברייתא. Braita. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, he said to him, כולי האי נמי? Kulei hai
nami? That far you're going to go? Now what exactly was that
question? So רש"י Rashi says א, Aleph, like who said you're not
a barbarian? Don't start patting yourself on the back.
Or
that it's not appropriate to make the ברכה Bracha for. When it
comes to a non-Jew or a woman, there's a different level of
מצוות, mitzvot. but here it's not really a different level of obligation,
so it really doesn't fit in the same category. A better way
perhaps of saying that or a different way of saying that is
that the שלא עשני Shelo Asani is about a status that somebody
is born with, the reality somebody is born with. The idea about
being an ignoramus or a תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham is something that
is in your control. So don't go making a ברכה Bracha for
something that was or was not in your control, that's in your
control. It's thanking God for the natural way that God has made
things. Okay, אמר ליה ואלא מאי מברך? Amar lei v'ela mai mevarech?
So what ברכה Bracha should I make? שלא עשני עבד, Shelo Asani
Eved, I did not make me a slave, and that of course
is the one that we do make. And similar to maybe some
people weren't born slaves, maybe they were captured and turned into slaves
as we know happened in society, other people were born slaves, but
either way it was not something in their control. Okay, so maybe
that's really what the critique was of the ברכה Bracha of שלא
עשני בור. Shelo Asani Bor. So now the pushback was היינו אשה,
Hainu Isha, that is similar, I'll read it this way, to the
sense of אשה, Isha, that the reason we are saying שלא עשני
אשה Shelo Asani Isha is because a woman has fewer מצוות mitzvot,
obligation than men. So that's already incorporated in that idea that I
was effectively a man with the full level of מצוות mitzvot, obligations.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, עבד זיל טפי, Eved zil tfei,
a slave nevertheless is of a lower social status than a woman.
So obviously it's not just all about the מצווה Mitzvah obligation. Anyway,
certainly a challenging גמרא Gemara for our contemporary sensibilities and there is
much, much, much literature on this. Okay, top of מ"ד ע"א. Mem-Dalet
Amud Aleph. תנו
רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught, חלזון זהו, Chilazon zehu, חלזון, Chilazon,
the
חלזון, Chilazon, גופו דומה לים, gufo domeh layam, its body is similar
to the ocean. Now חלזון Chilazon is understood as today's a certain
type of a snail. Obviously there's a lot of literature, a lot
of history debate about that, but anyway this snail is not itself
blue. So גופו דומה לים gufo domeh layam might mean that the
the ink that you make from it, the dye that you make
from it is similar to the color of the ocean that we
know. וברייתו דומה לדג, u'vriato domeh ledag, it is created similar to
a
fish. That led the רדזינר רבי Radziner Rebbe to think that it
was a type of fish, not a snail. It might be referring
to the actual animal that's inside of the shell of the snail.
ועולה אחת לשבעים שנה, v'oleh achat leshivim shana, and it comes up
once every 70 years it washes on shore. ובדמו צובעין תכלת, u'vidamo
tzovin techelet, and you use its blood to create תכלת, which is
of course. The point here.
לפיכך דמיו יקרים lefigach damav yakarim and therefore because it is so
hard and precious it is very it is very expensive.
תניא אמר רבי נתן amar Rabbi Natan אין לך כל מצוה קלה
שבתורה ein lecha kol mitzvah kalah shebatorah you do not have even
the most trivial mitzvah in the Torah, the easiest to perform, שאין
מתן שכרה בעולם הזה ולעולם הבא she'ein matan secharah ba'olam hazeh ule'olam
haba
בעולם הזה כמה ולעולם הבא איני יודע כמה. ba'olam hazeh kamah ule'olam
haba eini yodea kamah. So it seems to be the way that
we read it. Different גרסאות girsos as one has בעולם הזה ובעולם
הבא אבל איני יודע כמה. ba'olam hazeh ube'olam haba aval eini yodea
kamah. So either that you do not that it does not have
both reward in this world and in the world to come, כמה
kamah but I don't know how much, or it seems actually the
more proper reading is that you don't have it doesn't have its
reward in this world and as far as the world to come,
I can't even begin to estimate what the reward will be. Okay.
צא ולמד ממצות ציצית tze ulemad mimitzvas tzitzis go and learn from
the mitzvah of ציצית. tzitzit
מעשה באדם אחד maaseh be'adam echad this is an extremely famous story
I would be shocked if people have not heard this already. Story
with a certain man שהיה זהיר במצות ציצית shehayah zahir bemitzvas tzitzis
that he was very very careful when it came to the mitzvah
of
ציצית. tzitzit שמע שיש זונה בכרכי הים shama sheyesh zonah bekerachei hayam
but he had other weaknesses, okay he had not other he had
weaknesses,
and he heard that there was this prostitute over in the faraway
isles שנוטלת ארבע מאות זוזים בשכרה shenoteles arba meos zuzim bisecharah that
would take 400 gold coins for her fee. שיגר לה ארבע מאות
זוזים shigar lah arba meos zuzim he sent her these 400 gold
coins וקבע לה זמן vekeva lah zeman and he made an appointment
went to go to be with her. כשהגיע זמנו keshehigia zemano when
his appointment the date of his appointment came
בא וישב על הפתח ba veyashav al hapetach he went and he
waited by the doorway till he was allowed in. נכנסה שפחתה ואמרה
לה nichnesah shifchatah ve'amrah lah so this woman's this
prostitute's maidservant came and said to her אותו אדם ששיגר לך ארבע
מאות זוזים בא וישב על הפתח oso adam sheshigar lach arba meos
zuzim ba veyashav al hapetach that man that sent you 400 zuzim
your appointment is here, today's appointment is here.
אמרה היא amrah hi so she the prostitute said back יכנס yikanes
let him enter in. Like okay fine show him in. נכנס nichnas
he entered in. הציעה לו שבע מטות hetziah lo sheva mitos she
laid out for him seven beds שש של כסף ואחת של זהב
shesh shel kesef ve'achas shel zahav six of them were
silver and the top one was of gold ובין כל אחת ואחת
סולם של כסף ubein kol achas ve'achas sulam shel kesef and between
each one they were sort of one was at a higher level
than the next there was a silver ladder between them each
one ועליונה של זהב ve'elyonah shel zahav and the last one was
a golden ladder building up the anticipation and the effort to get
to this prostitute. Also I must say because this is going to
tie into the idea of ציצית tzitzit I can't help but thinking
about how
the one of the ideas about where we get the number 13
in terms of the wrappings of the ציצית tzitzit are the seven
heavenly רקיעות rekiyos you know which are like beds, right they're like
flat horizontal things and the six spaces between them. So I think
that that might be a little intended here as sort of the
opposite echo of that.
Okay.
עלתה וישבה על גבי עליונה alsah veyashvah al gabi elyonah so she
went and she sat on the top bed the golden one
כשהיא ערומה keshehi arumah and she was there waiting for him naked.
ואף הוא עלה לישב ערום כנגדה ve'af hu alah layshav arom kenegdah
and he was also going up and he planned these ladders to
go and to become and to be naked next to her with
her. באו ארבע ציציותיו bau arba tzitziosav as he was climbing up
the ladders and the four his four corners of the ציצית tzitzit
came or maybe as he was taking off his garment could be,
he was removing his garment and as he was pulling his cloak
off וטפחו לו על פניו vetapchu lo al panav the four ציציות
tzitzios came and hit him in the face. נשמט וישב לו על
גבי קרקע nishmat veyashav lo al gabi karka so he he was
overwhelmed by a sense of remorse or came he sort of broke
the spell of the lust and he came to his more sort
of rational or responsible self and he went and he went down
from the ladders and he sat on the ground. ואף היא נשמטה
וישבה על גבי קרקע ve'af hi nishmetah veyashvah al gabi karka she
saw the guy isn't coming up to me so she wanted to
find out what the story was so she went down and she
sat next to him on the floor. אמרה לו amrah lo and
she said to him גפה של רומי gapah shel Romi by
the like by the god of Rome that's how רש״י Rashi understands
what the word גפה gapah means שאיני מניחך she'eini manichacha I will
not leave you alone עד שתאמר לי מה מום ראית בי ad
shetomar li mah mum raisa bi until you tell me what blemish
you found in me how is it that you rejected me, she
was feeling very rejected.
אמר לה amar lah he said to
her העבודה ha'avodah in truth, forsooth. שלא ראיתי אשה יפה כמותך, shelo
ra'iti ishah yafah kemotech, I've never seen a woman as beautiful as
you, אלא, ela, but, מצוה אחת ציוונו ה' אלוקינו, mitzvah achat tzivanu
Hashem Elokeinu, God commanded us in one מצוה, mitzvah, וציצית שמה, v'tzitzit
shemah, and it is not only one מצוה, mitzvah, but there is
one מצוה mitzvah he commanded us, and it is called ציצית, tzitzit
וכתיב בה, v'chtiv bah, it says in it, אני ה' אלוקיכם, Ani
Hashem Elokeichem, שתי פעמים, shtei pe'amim, last פסוק, right? אני ה' אלוקיכם
אשר הוצאתי אתכם מארץ מצרים להיות לכם לאלוקים אני ה' אלוקיכם. Ani
Hashem Elokeichem asher hotzeiti etchem mei'eretz Mitzrayim lihyot lachem l'Elokim Ani Hashem
Elokeichem. So it is very much emphasizing that the wearing of ציצית
tzitzit to keep us cognizant of God and our responsibilities to God.
Interestingly, what he doesn't quote, but it's worth mentioning is of course
by the ציצית tzitzit it says ולא תתורו אחרי לבבכם ואחרי עיניכם
אשר אתם זונים אחריהם, v'lo taturu acharei l'vavchem v'acharei eineichem asher atem
zonim achareihem, you should not stray after your eyes which you are
fornicating after. So the idea of seeing, desire, lust, fornication, okay, anyway,
it says אני ה' אלוקיכם. Ani Hashem Elokeichem. אני הוא שעתיד להיפרע,
Ani hu she'atid l'hipara, and what that is telling us is God
is reminding us, you know, that the ציצית tzitzit, should remind us
that I eventually will seek, will punish people who
transgress. אני הוא שעתיד לשלם שכר, Ani hu she'atid l'shalem sachar, and
I will reward people who keep the מצוות. עכשיו, Achshav, and now
these four
ציצית tzitzit נדמו עלי כארבעה עדים, nidmu alai k'arba'ah edim, they are
like four witnesses, you know, coming to exhort me and to testify,
each two witnesses for being punished and two witnesses for reward, what
will be the consequence if I, you know, of my actions.
So אמרה לו, amrah lo, she said to him, איני מניחתך עד
שתאמר לי מה שמך, eini manichatcha ad she-tomar li mah shimcha, I
will not, she was so overwhelmed by this and by, you know,
how his this religious awakening that he had that she said, I
will not, you know, abandon you until you tell me what is
your name ומה שם עירך, u-mah shem irecha, where you come from
ומה שם רבך, u-mah shem rabbecha, what's your teacher's name, like where
did you learn like this
morality that it is, you know, and that is pulling you back
from this from me that you so, you know, passionately desire? ומה
שם מדרשך, u-mah shem midrashcha, where's your house of study שאתה למד
בו תורה, she-ata lomed bo Torah, that you learn Torah? So obviously,
you know, did she know the idea of תורה? Torah? Did he
tell her? Is that being inserted obviously in the story? Anyway, כתב
ונתן בידה, katav v'natan b'yadah, so he wrote out his address and
his name, he gave her the information, okay,
וכתב בידה. v'katav b'yadah. And then he went home. עמדה וחילקה כל
נכסיה, amdah v'chilkah kol nechasyeiha, so she got up and she after
this she divided her property, שליש למלכות, shlish l'malchut, a third she
gave to the government. We're going to see she wants to convert,
and רש"י Rashi says that was necessary to give to the government
that they would allow her to
convert. ושליש לעניים, v'shlish l'aniyim, a third to the poor. Maybe she
was inspired by the righteous act of this individual. ושליש נטלה בידה,
v'shlish natlah b'yadah, a third she kept for herself, and חוץ מאותן
מצעות, chutz mei'otan matza'ot, and with one thing she did not give
away was also these bedspreads, you know, that she had laid out
for him. ובאה לבית מדרשו של רבי חייא, u-ba'ah l'veit midrasho shel
Rabbi Chiya, she came to the בית מדרש beit midrash of רבי
חייא. Rabbi Chiya. אמרה לו, amrah lo, and she said to him,
רבי, צווי עלי ויעשוני גיורת. Rebbi, tzavei alai v'ya'asuni giyoret. She said,
רבי, you know, assign some students to me that they should teach
me תורה Torah and I should become a גיורת. giyoret. I want
to convert. אמר לה, amar lah, he said to her, בתי, שמא
עיניך נתת באחד מן התלמידים? biti, shema eineiyich natat b'echad min ha-talmidim?
Perhaps you are doing this because you desire one of the students,
you know, and you're not supposed to convert for the purposes of
marriage? So הוציאה כתב מידה, hotzi'ah k'tav miyadah, she took out this
thing that the student had written ונתנה לו, v'natnah lo, and gave
it to him. אמר לה, amar lah, and he presumably explained everything
that had happened. So it's and the point being not yes, I
want to marry that student, but I was so inspired by your
תורה, Torah, your teaching, your morality, you know, that this is drawing
me closer to תורה Torah and I now want to be Jewish
as a result. So אמר לה, amar lah, he said to her,
לכי זכי במקחך. lechi zechi b'mikchachech. Go and, you know, take possession
of your purchase, meaning yes, I will convert you and you always
can also marry this man that has so inspired you through his
righteousness or through his awakening.
אותן מצעות שהציעה לו באיסור, otan matza'ot she-hetzi'ah lo b'issur, and now
the story ends that those bedspreads that she had laid out for
him in prohibition, when they were going to be doing something in
violation, you know, not marital, you know, intimacy, you know, not in
the context of marriage, but just having, you know, a like fornication.
So instead of in that context, שהציעה לו באיסור, she-hetzi'ah lo b'issur,
הציעה לו בהיתר, hetzi'ah lo b'heter, now she spread out for him
in a permissible and a sanctified way in the context of marriage.
Okay, and there's also maybe something here about again the spreading and
the cloth and the ציצית tzitzit and so on. Okay, so זה
מתן שכר בעולם הזה, zeh matan sachar ba-olam ha-zeh, that is the
reward in this world, you know, the reward that it I don't
know if the reward that it led her to convert and it
inspired her, presumably the point is also the reward that because he
was held himself back from transgressing and doing this in a prohibition,
he was rewarded to have that same opportunity come to him in
a way of permissibility, in a way of sanctity. ולעולם הבא איני
יודע. u-l'olam ha-ba eini yodei'a. If that's in this world, I can't
even imagine what the reward will be for the world to come.
Okay, very famous famous story.
אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, said רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, now
going, going from that sort of beautiful, inspiring, elevating story to a
little straight הלכה. halacha. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, טלית שאולה
כל שלשים יום פטור מן הציצית, talit she-ulah kol shloshim yom patur
min ha-tzitzit, a borrowed טלית talit is exempt from ציצית tzitzit for
30 days. מכאן
ואילך חייב בה, mi-kan ve-eilech chayav bah, beyond that it is obligated.
תוספות Tosafot says that it really is always exempt because by טלית
talit we the we have a פסוק that is, you know, that
basically says,
you know it says על ארבע כנפות כסותך, al arba kanfot kesutcha,
your garment, that you have to own it. Nevertheless, after 30 days
people will think, this is what תוספות Tosafot explains, will think it's
yours. You've been wearing it for 30 days and therefore you have
to put ציצית tzitzit, on it afterwards, even though דאורייתא de-Oraita it
is exempt. Okay, maybe also after 30 days you're starting to feel
a degree of ownership, even though you don't genuinely own it, and
therefore you're obligated. Okay, so that's another final ציצית tzitzit. הלכה halacha
and we'll end now with something taking us beyond ציצית and taking
us, jumping us back to the מזוזה mezuzah discussion.
תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we've taught similarly, הדר בפונדק בארץ
ישראל, ha-dar be-pundak be-Eretz Yisrael, if somebody is staying in an inn
in Israel, והשוכר בית בחוץ לארץ, ve-hasocher bayit be-chutz la-aretz, or renting
a house in חוץ לארץ, chutz la-aretz, כל שלשים יום פטור מן
המזוזה. kol shloshim yom patur min ha-mezuzah. The first 30 days you're
exempt. מכאן ואילך חייב, mi-kan ve-eilech chayav, beyond that you're obligated. אבל
השוכר בית בארץ ישראל, aval hasocher bayit be-Eretz Yisrael, but if you
rent a house in the land of Israel, עושה מזוזה לאלתר משום
ישוב ארץ ישראל, oseh mezuzah la-altar mishum yishuv Eretz Yisrael, you make
a מזוזה mezuzah immediately because of settling the land of Israel. So
this is a little debate, or not a little, this is debated
in terms of what some of these mean and what some of
the principles here is. Some say that the same way, you know,
you're exempt דאורייתא de-Oraita for a
borrowed טלית, talit, you're exempt דאורייתא de-Oraita for a rented house. It
says מזוזות ביתך, mezuzot beitecha, so ביתך, beitecha, your house, you have
to own it. And therefore it's דאורייתא de-Oraita you're exempt. Nevertheless, after
30 days you're obligated, either because then similar reasons, maybe appearance, people
will think it's yours, or maybe just your relationship to it, you
feel a degree of ownership, we obligate you after 30 days. And
in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, okay, we'll get to why ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael is different in a minute. That's one way of understanding
it. Another way is, no, by מזוזה mezuzah you actually are exempt,
excuse me, are obligated מן התורה, min ha-Torah, when you rent it.
Rental is obligated מן התורה. min ha-Torah. But nevertheless, it is not
considered to be a בית דירה, beit dirah, meaning you own it,
but it's not yet your domicile. You know, you need to nest,
you need to settle in it, you need to be there before
it is something that it's your, you feel it's home, right? That
takes time. It takes 30 days. So yes, you are חייב דאורייתא
chayav de-Oraita but it takes 30 days until you feel that it
is home.
And that's why you're not חייב until 30 days. That's in terms
of the 30 days. Either דרבנן, de-rabbanan, the whole obligation is דרבנן,
de-rabbanan, or the obligation is דאורייתא de-Oraita but you have to be
settled in it, and it takes 30 days. There's an interesting question
of if your lease is from the get-go more than 30 days,
are you obligated from the get-go,
or you know, or can you if you want, can you make
a ברכה bracha from the get-go or do you only make a
ברכה bracha after 30 days? You know, all this is debated. But
the general assumption here in the simple language of the גמרא Gemara
is that there's not an obligation no matter how long your lease
is for until you've been there for 30 days. In terms of
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, why is that different? The way רש"י explains
it is if we require you to get a מזוזה, mezuzah, that
will be more likely that you will stay in the house. You
know, if you don't have a מזוזה mezuzah it's easier to leave.
But once you have a מזוזה mezuzah you don't want to leave
because you'll have to leave the מזוזה mezuzah behind. And if you
do leave, it'll be encouraging for somebody to move in. So these
are sort of like incentives to stay and to dwell in Israel
or for somebody else to move in. Another way of saying it
is not to read it as an incentive, but to read it
that because of the obligation to live in Israel,
even when you're there for just a short period of time, it's
already coming home, like you're already home, it's already settled. That normally
the phrase משום ישוב ארץ ישראל mishum yishuv Eretz Yisrael more means
it's an incentive rather than it's a substantive
reason why the הלכה halacha would be different. Okay, so that is
the end of our wonderful discussion of ציצית, and now we end
the whole discussion of תפילין, tefillin, מזוזה, mezuzah, ספר תורה, sefer Torah,
תפילין, tefillin, מזוזה, mezuzah, ציצית with a short discussion now of one
final discussion here relating to תפילין. tefillin. תפלה של יד אינה מעכבת,
Tefillah shel yad einah me'akevet, the תפילין tefillin of the hand תפילין
tefillin does not hold back, not having it does not prevent you
from doing the head תפילין tefillin and vice versa. אמר רב חסדא,
Amar Rav Chisda, said רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, לא שנו אלא שיש
לו. lo shanu ela she-yesh lo. When is that, that having one
doesn't prevent you from doing the מצוה? mitzvah? Is if you have...
both of them, but right now for some reason, you know, you're
only putting on one. So you did that מצוה. mitzvah. אבל אין
לו, aval ein lo, if you don't have both of them, מעכבת.
me'akevet. Then, you know, then you're, then it does hold it back,
and doing one you're not יוצא yotzei because you don't have the
other. And that's strange, why if they're separate מצוות, why should whether
you own them or not own them determine whether or not you've
done the מצוה mitzvah of the one that you do have? Which
is what the גמרא Gemara. says.
אמרו לו, Amru lo, so they said to רב חסדא, Rav Chisda,
אמרת, amarta, did you really say this?
אמר להו, Amar lehu, he said back, לא, lo, I didn't say
it. אלא מאן דלית ליה תרי מצוות חדא מצוה נמי לא ליעביד?
Ella man d'leit lei t'rei mitzvot chada mitzvah nami lo l'avid? So
what, you know, if somebody doesn't have two מצוות, should they not
do one מצוה? mitzvah? Of course, even if you don't have the
other one, you're יוצא yotzei the one that you do have. ומעיקרא
מאי סבר? U'me'ikara mai savar? Now,
when it says that he said he didn't say it, it seems
like the גמרא Gemara knew that it didn't mean he didn't say
it, it meant he reversed himself. When he was challenged, he reversed
himself. So initially why did he say you're not יוצא? yotzei? So
גזירה שמא יפשע, gezeira shema yifsha, because he thought that if you
tell somebody if you only own one, you're יוצא yotzei with at
least that one מצוה, mitzvah, then there's no incentive for the person
to buy the other. So we'll tell people if you only own
one, you're not even יוצא yotzei that one, you need to own
both. And that will be an incentive for people to make sure
that they own both. Okay, but in the end the decision was
that incentivizing people was not worth telling somebody not to do the
מצוה mitzvah when they had the opportunity to do it. Okay, אמר
רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, said רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, כל שאינו
מניח תפילין עובר בשמונה עשה. kol she'eino mani'ach tefillin over b'shmonah asei.
If you don't put on תפילין, tefillin, you transgress seven, eight עשה,
aseis, because by the תפילין tefillin it says, you know, וקשרתם לאות
והיו לטוטפות והיו לזיכרון וקשרתם ושמרת את החוקה הזאת. u'kshartem l'ot v'hayu
l'totafot v'hayu l'zikaron u'kshartem v'shamarta et hachuka hazot. There are four פרשיות.
parshiyot. If you add up the verbs, there are eight times it
says to put on תפילין. tefillin. You know, four for, you know,
for the most part, four for the של יד shel yad and
four for the של ראש. shel rosh.
One or two of them are more general. וכל שאין לו ציצית,
v'chol she'ein lo tzitzit, and anybody who doesn't wear ציצית בבגדו, b'vigdo,
meaning you have a garment that's obligated but you don't have the
ציצית on it, עובר בחמישה עשה, over b'chamisha asei, transgresses five עשה.
aseis. רש״י Rashi said, lists them, last רש״י Rashi on the page,
ועשו, v'asu, you should make ציצית, ונתנו, v'natnu, you should put the
תכלת, והיה לכם לציצית, v'haya lachem l'tzitzit, וראיתם, u're'item, you shall see
them, וגדילים תעשה לך. u'gdilim ta'aseh lach. So five עשה. aseis. כל
שאין לו מזוזה בפתחו עובר בשני עשה וכתבתם וכתבתם. kol she'ein lo
mezuzah b'pitcho over b'shnei asei u'ktavtam u'ktavtam. If you don't have a
מזוזה, mezuzah, you transgress two עשה aseis because it says you should
write them for מזוזות mezuzot in each פרשה parsha of the, the
פרשה parsha of the שמע and then the פרשה parsha of והיה
אם שמוע. v'haya im shamo'a. Okay, so that's what you transgress. וכל
כהן שאינו עולה לדוכן עובר בג׳ עשה. v'chol kohen she'eino oleh l'duchan
over b'gimmel asei. I'm sorry, I skipped one. וכל כהן שאינו עולה
לדוכן עובר בג׳ עשה. v'chol kohen she'eino oleh l'duchan over b'gimmel asei.
If a כהן kohen doesn't go up to the דוכן, duchan, he
transgresses three עשה. aseis. Right, it says אמור להם כה תברכו ושמו
את שמי. amor lahem koh tevarachu v'samu et shmi. וכל שאין לו
מזוזה בפתחו עובר בשני עשה וכתבתם וכתבתם.
v'chol she'ein lo mezuzah b'pitcho over
b'shnei
asei u'ktavtam u'ktavtam. Okay, interesting sneak, fitting in the כהן kohen here,
doesn't sort of seem to go with the rest of the תפילין,
tefillin, מזוזה, mezuzah, and טלית tallit and ציצית. Anyway. ואמר ריש לקיש,
V'amar Reish Lakish, and says ריש
לקיש, Reish Lakish, כל המניח תפילין מאריך ימים, kol hamani'ach tefillin ma'arich
yamim, whoever puts on תפילין tefillin will have long days, שנאמר, Shene'emar,
as the verse says, top of מד עמוד ב, mem daled amud
bet, ה׳ עליהם יחיו, Hashem aleihem yichyu, God will on them they
will live, so God on them is the תפילין tefillin of the
ראש, rosh, ולכל בהן חיי
רוחי, u'l'chol bahen chiyei ruchi, and any, and all those to have
in them my, the spirit of my, of my life, or my
life spirit, ותחלימני והחייני, v'tachlimeni v'hachayeni, and you know, it healed me
and it, and it gave me life. Okay, and the מהרש״א Maharsha
says, you know, if the ה׳ עליהם Hashem aleihem is the תפילין
של ראש, tefillin shel rosh, וחיי רוחי v'chiyei ruchi is the רוח,
ruach, the spirit, is a תפילין של יד, tefillin shel yad, which
is opposite the heart, you know, more speaking to our spirit. So
that was the end of these beautiful discussions of ספר תורה, sefer
Torah, תפילין, tefillin, מזוזה, mezuzah, and טלית. tallit. Now back to things
relating more to מנחות. menachot
Still though in the context of something A being מעכב me'akev B.
Okay, הסולת והשמן אין מעכבין את היין. hasolet v'hashemen ein me'akvin et
hayayin. When it comes to the מנחת נסכים, minchat nesachim, the מנחות
that were brought together with the קרבנות, korbanot, like with an עולה
olah and whatever, it says that if you have the flour and
the oil, that's, you know, the תורה Torah says how much flour,
how much oil plus you know and that you put on the
מזבח mizbeach and you burn it plus the wine that you pour
on the מזבח. mizbeach. So those are two separate things, both have
to be brought but they are not interdependent. So not having the
flour and the oil does not prevent you from doing the wine
for the מנחת נסכים. minchat nesachim. ולא היין מעכבן, v'lo hayayin me'akvan,
and not having the wine doesn't prevent you from bringing the flour
and the oil. המתנות שעל מזבח החיצון אין מעכבות זו את זו.
hamatanot she'al mizbeach hachitzon ein me'akvot zu et zu. We had this
in זבחים Zevachim before, the placing of blood on the outer altar,
whether it's the four placings of the חטאת. chatat. as or the
two throwings of the blood of the other קרבנות, korbanot, the מתנות
matnot probably normal, you know, classically refer to the חטאת. Chatat. They
do not prevent each other, you know, they're not all required. Not
doing all of them does not prevent you from being יוצא yotze
even if you just had one, you will be יוצא. yotze. That
we learned much earlier in זבחים. Zvachim. Okay, let's see the גמרא.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught: ומנחתם ונסכיהם, u'minchasam v'niskeihem, הוי
מנחה ואחר כך הוי נסכים. havei mincha v'achar kach havei nisachim.
So what is the order? It's not even really addressing the משנה,
Mishna, but it's saying when you're bringing the flour and oil and
then the wine for these מנחת נסכים, Minchas Nesachim, which do you
put on the מזבח mizbe'ach first? So the first דרשה drasha is
first it says the מנחה mincha and then it says the נסכים,
nisachim, the libations, so first the מנחה mincha and then the נסכים.
nisachim. רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, Rebbi says, זבח ונסכים, zevach u'nisachim, he
quotes a different פסוק, the sacrifice and the libations, הוי זבח ואחר
כך הוי נסכים. havei zevach v'achar kach havei nisachim. No, after the
sacrifice, the animal, then the libations, and the מנחה mincha comes after.
So a debate: first מנחה mincha and then the libations, or libations
and then מנחה. mincha.
Okay, ורבי דאמי הכתיב ומנחתם ונסכיהם. v'Rebbi da'ami hakesiv u'minchasam v'niskeihem. What
does Rebbi do with the פסוק ומנחתם ונסכיהם pasuk u'minchasam v'niskeihem which
seems to say the order is first the מנחה, mincha, then the
libations? ההוא מיבעי ליה, hahu mibaye leh, no, that you need it
for a different דרשה. drasha. ומנחתם ונסכיהם בלילה ומנחתם ונסכיהם אפילו למחר,
u'minchasam v'niskeihem balaylah u'minchasam v'niskeihem afilu l'machar,
that we learned that extra ומנחתם ונסכיהם, u'minchasam v'niskeihem, and תוספות has
a whole long discussion which ומנחתם ונסכיהם u'minchasam v'niskeihem are we דרשנין,
dorshenin, it appears so many different times and so many different ways
in the פסוקים, psukim, but anyway that is teaching you not the
order, it is teaching you that the מנחה mincha and the נסכים
nisachim can be separate from the קרבן. korban. That you can bring
the קרבן korban in the day and the מנחה mincha and the
נסכים nisachim in the night. You can bring the קרבן korban on
day one and bring the מנחה mincha and the נסכים nisachim on
a different day. Now all of that is when you bring them
separately to begin this, to begin with. When you bring them at
the same time, you know, into the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, then
they all have to be brought together. Okay, but that's the דרשה
drasha that they can be brought separately even at night, even at
a different time. ורבנן נמי הכתיב זבח ונסכים? v'Rabbanan nami hakesiv zevach
u'nisachim? And what about the rabbis, what do they do with זבח
ונסכים? zevach u'nisachim? That seems to be coming to teach you that
the libations come first. ההוא מיבעי ליה לכדזעירא. hahu mibaye leh l'chidezeira.
No, they need that not to tell you order, but to tell
you a completely separate דרשה drasha of זעירא. Zeira. דאמר זעירא, d'amar
Zeira, Zeira says, אין נסכים מתקדשים אלא בשחיטת
הזבח.
ein nisachim miskadshim ela
bishchitas hazevach. זבח ונסכים zevach u'nisachim tells you that those come as
a package, that the נסכים, nisachim, the מנחה mincha and the wine
that you bring together with the קרבן, korban, they only get sanctified
when you שחט shacht the קרבן. korban. Now there's a question what
that means. It might mean they only get sanctified so that, you
know, that they become פסול pasul if you bring them out of
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, a קדושת הגוף. kdushas haguf.
Another interpretation in the ראשונים Rishonim is: no, it means that you
can switch them to another קרבן korban until you שחט shacht the
קרבן, korban, but once you שחט shacht the קרבן korban they're brought
with, they become linked to that קרבן. korban. Okay, but that's to
tell you that they come as a package. ורבי נמי מיבעי ליה
לכדזעירא. v'Rebbi nami mibaye leh l'chidezeira. One minute. Okay, but you said
many other things we learned from these פסוקים. psukim. Everybody needs to
learn these things from these פסוקים. psukim. Rebbi needs the פסוק of
זבח ונסכים zevach u'nisachim to tell me the teaching of זעירא Zeira
that they come as a package. ורבנן נמי מיבעי להו למנחתם ונסכיהם
בלילה מנחתם ונסכיהם אפילו למחר. v'Rabbanan nami mibaye lehu l'u'minchasam v'niskeihem balaylah
u'minchasam v'niskeihem afilu l'machar. And the rabbis, ומנחתם ונסכיהם, u'minchasam v'niskeihem,
how do they use that to teach you the order? They also
need that to teach you that the מנחה mincha and נסכים nisachim
can come at night and on a different day. So these פסוקים
psukim are already spoken for, so they can't be the פסוקים psukim
that are the basis of the debate of Rebbi and the rabbis.
אלא היינו טעמייהו דרבנן. ela haynu tamaihu d'Rabbanan. Fine, here's the reason
of the rabbis. דכתיב, d'chesiv, it says. Now the funny thing is
the ברייתא braisa actually explicitly said that they were basing themselves on
this פסוק. But the גמרא says because we need the פסוק elsewhere
we're going to say they're really basing themselves on a different
פסוק. Okay, אלא היינו טעמא דרבנן דכתיב עולה ומנחה. ela haynu tama
d'Rabbanan d'chesiv olah u'mincha. It says עולה ומנחה זבח ונסכים דבר יום
ביומו. olah u'mincha zevach u'nisachim dvar yom b'yomo. So עולה ומנחה olah
u'mincha says after the עולה olah comes the מנחה, mincha, so that's
why מנחה mincha comes first. ורבי נמי הכתיב עולה ומנחה. v'Rebbi nami
hakesiv olah u'mincha. So what does Rebbi do with that? אלא בבואם
עם הזבח דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דמנחה ואחר כך נסכים. ela b'vo'am
im hazevach d'chulei alma lo pligi d'mincha v'achar kach nisachim. דכתיב עולה
ומנחה. d'chesiv olah u'mincha. Fine, you're right. עולה ומנחה olah u'mincha is
such a powerful combination that everybody agrees that when you bring it
at the same time and together with the קרבן, korban, after you
do the עולה olah the first thing you do is you do
the מנחה mincha and only afterwards do you pour the wine libations.
Okay, that's what עולה ומנחה olah u'mincha teaches you.
כי פליגי בבואם בפני עצמן. ki pligi b'vo'am bifnei atzman. When do
they argue? When you're going to bring them separate from the קרבן.
korban. You're obligated to bring them because you brought the קרבן, korban,
but you're bringing them on a different day. So that's and then
it's really just a סברא svara debate. Okay, רבנן סברי מדבאים עם
הזבח מנחה ואחר כך נסכים בפני עצמן מנחה ואחר כך נסכים. Rabanan
savri midevaim im hazevach mincha veachar kach nesachim bifnei atzman mincha veachar
kach nesachim.
Since when they come with the קרבן, korban, we learn from עולה
ומנחה Olah u'Mincha that first you bring the מנחה mincha and then
the libations. The same order will apply when you bring them separate.
For רבי, but רבי would say back no, התם הוא דאיידי דאתחיל
באכילה גמר לה לכולה מילתא דאכילה. hasam hu de'aidi de'atchil beachilah gemar
lah lechulah miltah de'achilah. There there's a logic, you start with the
קרבן, korban, it's food, so the thing next thing you bring is
the מנחה mincha which is also food, something that is eaten, and
you leave the wine, the drink, for afterwards. So when they're coming
together, it makes sense, עולה Olah and then, you know, מנחה mincha
and the נסכים nesachim comes later. But עדיפי, adifi, so that's better.
I'm
sorry, אבל בפני עצמן, aval bifnei atzman, but when they're coming separate
and independent, נסכים עדיפי, nesachim adifi, it makes sense to start with
the wine. Why? הוא דמיתאמרא שירה עליהו, hu demis'amra shirah aleihu, since
that is when the, you know, שירה shirah is said, when the,
when you're pouring out the wine of the נסכים. nesachim. So, you
know, so therefore, you know, it is wine is more important. It's
also why, you know, you make kiddush over wine, אין אומרים שירה
אלא על היין, ein omrim shirah ela al hayayin, etc. And therefore
wine is more important and therefore you will bring the wine first.
Okay, that's because that is when the לויים Levi'im sing the שירה.
shirah. Okay, last point. המנחות המתנות שעל המזבח החיצון אין מעכבות זו
את זו. Hamenachos hamatanos she'al hamizbe'ach hachitzon ein me'akvos zu es zu.
The four placements of the חטאת chatas are not מעכב, me'akev, even
one is good, works. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, מנין לכל הניתנים על
המזבח החיצון שניתנו מתנה אחת שכיפר? minayin lechol hanisanim al hamizbe'ach hachitzon
shenisnu matanah achas shekiper? How do you know all things that are
put on the outer altar, whether חטאת, chatas, whether עולה, Olah, whatever
it is, in the end even one placement of blood works? שנאמר,
the פסוק says, ודם זבחיך ישפך על מזבח ה' אלהיך. vedam zvacheicha
yishapech al mizbe'ach Hashem Elokecha. The blood of your sacrifices you shall
pour. Just one pouring, just one placement suffices בדיעבד. bedi'eved. Okay, we
will end with this for now.